so welcome everyone to another episode
of voices with rebecky it's my great
pleasure to have my friend and dialogic
partner you've seen him in many of my
conversations Jordan Hall it's one of
the great gifts of my awakening from the
meeting crisis series was I got to meet
and form a relationship with Jordan and
we've had an ongoing and I believe it's
mutually beneficial dialogue that's been
going on between us
and what I want to well what I what I
what we're both going to talk about I
just want to give you a bit of context
for that what we want to talk about is I
have as many of you know this project
and it's being exemplified in voices of
a key of trying to understand the set of
practices that I'm collectively calling
you know dialectic and how they afford
this emergent way of cultivating
collective intelligence into collective
wisdom and I call that deal logos the
work I'm doing with Chris and also with
Jordan that guy and Peter Lindberg and
some of you have also seen some
conversations I've had with and ursini
and Zack sign about this and and how
this has a connection to a revision aim
of what education means and then Jordan
has expressed that he's very interested
now in this this connection between
education more broadly understood as a
way I think maybe a better term might
even be you know like inculturation not
just education and how that intersects
with dialectic as a practice and via
logos as a phenomenon so is that a fair
representation burden of the context of
the discussion yeah that's great so I'm
gonna begin with what I step towards you
know before we started recording maybe
give you something to riff on because
I'm very interested in fact and I see if
dialectic as a practice in Villalobos as
a process is ultimately you know that
you're seeking information through
transformation the idea that we we only
can be informed by what transcends us by
going through a process of transfer
that's the only way and so trying to
reconfigure the notion of gathering
information and education and we linking
it back to transformation and then that
puts me into the notion that this is
ultimately an aspirational process this
transformation is the aspiration to
transcend who and what you are become
something other than you are and then
that leads me into this idea that we are
discussing about education and I think
Anzac seems to resonate with this -
education not being primary about
providing information but a40 a place in
which people can seriously play with
ways of life ways of being that will
afford afford that aspiration and
transformation and I see it as deeply
exemplified in Socratic practice a lot
of authors point out that a lot of the
dialogues often don't come to an
argumentative conclusion because the
arguments a lot of importance are not
actually focal what's focal what's
really being compared and Socrates is
exemplifying or ways of life ways of
being and the and the the enactment of
the logos is a way in which you get a
taste for a different way of being a
different way of thinking a different
way of seeing different way of being
with other people a different way right
a different way of living a different
way of life and so I'm very interested
deeply interested in this connection
between dialectic via logos
transformation enculturation and you
know this idea of Education being much
more about what used to be called virtue
mmhmm yeah very nice yeah it's a few
things that come up there are we have we
contend with the notion of enculturation
yeah immediately will come to mind is
the I think in many cases the the intent
or the accident of an endeavor to
generate a enculturation which Orient's
toward stasis
a culture that consciously endeavors to
enculturate itself without change right
right much of any education has that
characteristic you might say for example
there's a nice distinction between world
through what is relevant right in that
an education that is focused on true is
very much oriented towards stasis
because it assumes relevance as a basis
and then tries to get you those things
that are true subject in that relevance
educating focuses on relevance
recognizes that what is relevant may in
fact be changing continuously and our
job is to maintain a a coherent capacity
to be to end culture it to maintain in
it some kind of coherent integrity or
wholeness beingness of culture in a
context that is adaptive to it is really
actually changing and therefore is sort
of a surfing through reality without
saying that that Buckminster Fuller
raised and contra for exactly how he
said it it's like you know I'm a knot of
causation if this loop there's a lot of
cause like every every I'm a dynamic
phenomena of self replicating processes
but there's no moment at which if you
did like a frozen snapshot of me and
tried to say that was me you'd be wrong
like all the atoms that I breathe in and
breathe out every phenomenon that could
be considered material is just well it's
like a wave in the ocean right the wave
in the ocean is not the water molecules
it's the it's the process that's moving
through the way through the ocean and so
a culture which is able to consciously
be aware of this and endeavor to embody
a method of enculturation which has this
focus on virtue which is to say focus on
those aspects that are actually
invariant about hotland build up
creating something which is able to
identify relevance and cultivate
capacity to perceive relevance and then
respond to relevance in a generative
fashion ongoingly would be the or the
holy grail look at the end point of the
question of how do we actually learn
about learning something like that
and I was thinking about this we can
talk about deal logos which is that the
subject is actually how does one become
an agent a dll goes like that's the
that's the best zero
the first thing welfare you can enter
into deal luggage you must first become
an agent who can participate in via
logos then then the DA logos is
self-supporting because one of the one
of the loops of do logos is that it
it's the supports in yourself and those
who are participating increasing clarity
of how to be an agent e logos you get
that now for free if you're
participating with it then you get the
other stuff on top that's excellent so
there's three points that I want that I
want to first you said about relevance
and about agency so the first is that
that distinction you made is analogous
to distinction that I've been working on
I'm throwing out of the literature
especially the philosophy of science
literature and also the cognitive
science of wisdom literature which is
the distinction between knowledge and
understanding and so the idea is and
knowledge has it as its normativity you
know as you said the standard
normativity of truth especially when we
talk about propositional knowledge I
mean I think skills have power you know
perspectives of presidents and
participatory knowing has affordance
connectedness but putting that aside the
difference between knowledge and
understanding is that understanding is
it's emphasized and a lot of the people
they keep their stand towards this but
they're trying to unpack it has amended
the challenge understanding is to grasp
the significance of what you know which
immediately I have taken as you might
expect to be what you're talking about
grasping the relevance right grasping
the relevance of it and as you say not
in term just merely epistemic passion
but grasping it
existentially relevance not in the sense
of this is just interesting but
relevance in well this is where I will
commit my precious cognitive resources
my precious time my precious
relationships is this is where
I will you know I feel I have the best
chance the best bathroom a place in my
commitment so it's grasping the
significance and how it calls you into
commitment so this is version ending and
so there's and there's and then there's
parts to what's going on at
understanding because I think
understanding especially if you want it
to have that dynamic coupling to
emergence that you're talking about it's
all it's also going to be aligned with
aspiration because if you're feeling
called right and you're really
understanding then if there's any
epistemic humility in your sense of
relevance you're also understanding what
you do not yet drops what you do not yet
understand right usually the
understanding the understanding should
always be and this of course you know a
platonic theme it should always be on
the horizon of wonder it should always
be on the edge where you're right you
you have the horizon intelligibility you
see what you've grasped but you're also
realizing right in a relevant manner
what you have not yet grasped you have
an inkling I think is a great term for
it um so I think that's very important
and then that brings up your second
point I think because now we're talking
about agency we're talking about
aspiration we're talking about right
there's always this pairing when
something is disclosed which it means
more than I know it when something is
disclosed everything apart eager here
I'm grasping it's significant and then
there's a demand on there's a call to me
that how I have to transform right in
order to come into proper relationship
with what's emerging and then that's the
question of agency but you brought up
that I see the question of agency is you
know what the what kind of person do I
have to be in order to stay in contact
with this what's what what's emerging
yeah yeah so let's um so imagine so
we're we're in a so many crises is going
on right now that may mean memmer eight
them is itself a crisis the crisis that
I was just noticing is the crisis
information which is to say there was a
time when knowing stuff really mattered
a lot because it's very difficult to
know stuff and most people didn't know
most stuff and so if you had certain
stuff that you knew the other people
didn't know that was valuable these days
most stuff is already known by the
internet and so it's a matter of finding
it as it's much more important than
knowing it and sorry the visual image I
have here is the thing I'm trying to
figure out how to express it so it's um
the challenge is a challenge of learning
how to dance through a perpetually
changing space yes the the space of what
could be known
it's basically what is known as
expanding exponentially and so there is
no more power there is no more agency
really to be had by simply to know stuff
because it's whatever you know is a tiny
territory of an expanding universe and
increasingly available to anybody who
could in size the search for it so the
the new center of agency is this
capacity and gosh I wish I didn't just
lost the language you are using but it's
this capacity to to to follow that
threat to just to flow with to unfold
into a an expanding or a receding
horizon and it's thirdly its
skillfulness and I guess it's just a
capacitor even a disposition that's
probably it it's the skillfulness of
capacity and his disposition to orient
towards that perpetual renewal that
moving into the newness that has
happened and not to just sit here as The
Horizon recedes but actually to sail
with the horizon to turn the movement of
the horizon into a win the blows your
ship forward into that into that did
that new place that's a very very
different orientation a very different
sensibility of what it means
I think the actually it was maybe a bit
more clarity to the kinds of to the
essence of versus actually want to
return back to birth yeah I think that's
it i think i think the term i wanted to
use what you're talking about I mean I
think of a virtue I mean the original
meaning is you know the power and the
possib
right virtue right it's it's a it's a
it's a potency it's a potential that is
ready to action right yeah so and and
then what powers are we talking about
here I think you're talking about I I
would call it like a sensibility in a
sensitivity to what's to significance
like - like I said grasping what's
significant and then also you know there
there's the way in which you honed that
to your ability to actually commit so I
I'm thinking more about these two sides
like I said they're the sensing the
significance and then taking it
seriously I'm proposing this in fact as
the kind of normativity we should be
trying to use instead of the old
normativity x' we had foreknowledge
which were the normativity x' of
certainty and probability yeah yeah what
what do we take seriously like which is
not the same thing right so I've been
exploring a lot this notion of
plausibility there's two meanings of
plausibility one is just a synonym for
highly probable that's not what I'm
talking about there's a whole other
standard and people philosophers have
been talking about this where
plausibility means I take something
seriously it's something that I will
commit myself to I'm not saying it's
true I'm not even claiming it's certain
or even I'm not even sure what its
probabilities but what I'm it's worthy
of being taken seriously it has a
significance which is to say that is
that I will attend to it
I will venture into it I'll expand the
most precious resource in the universe
which is the finite amount of time that
I am on this earth or renting myself in
that direction which is okay that's an
ethical act that is that is the ethic
laughs yeah I'll excuse that pass that's
great and then let me just use a
different metaphor which is the knit
metaphor of network because what you're
talking about is it is it is a in an
Open Graph network the question for a
given node is what edges what edges
shall be formed and what communication
shall flow across those edges and the
question you're asking is that same
question like what is this shape of the
network so instead of thinking about
what is
tenth of the network we're actually
talking about what is the topology of
the network exactly is the primary
question yeah exactly
I don't weigh that that little insight
right there if you happen to be watching
this that's a very important one that's
a big insight I think so ultimately well
two things first of all on that and then
back on what you said about the ethical
aspect of this I think that that inside
I mean this is that sort of the core of
what I what I know what I take back I
think we also have to reconstruct is
I've been trying to do what we mean by
being rational and we don't mean you
know we are not going to hold ourselves
to the logical manipulation of
inferences because that's that's around
the normativity of certainty or at least
with induction probability instead what
should rationality mean it should mean
you know these fumes in the overcoming
of self-deception as much as possible
and the affording of of you know of good
connection as much as possible good
connectedness and so what I was getting
on there is that one of the primary
insights that makes that new sense of
rationality possible is that rationality
is about shifting off our fixation on
the products of our cognition and our
communication and coming to take a deep
interest and commitment to the process
and so I I think with that insight that
you just mentioned of shifting right
from the content to apology I think is I
think it's consonant with you know this
and I think it has to be you know if
we're if we're going to be reformulating
education we have to be reformulating
what rationality means and then I want
to know what you know the rationality of
plausibility as I'm using it to mean
that virtue of properly sensing the
significance and taking seriously in an
appropriate a wise manner I want to know
what what that looks like and then back
to the point then that you started with
I agree with you and this comes out of
iris Murdoch's the sovereignty of good
the primary ethical act is the act of
paying attention giving things their due
attention which is exactly what we're
talking about in my giving things the
attention they deserve
this isn't this is a different
conception of justice it's giving things
you know adjust attention just the right
amount of attention I'm playing with the
word just right but that's what she's
talking about in the sovereignty of the
good and so I think this isn't my thing
this is a deeply important virtue that
we're trying to zero in on it you know
it's got up its got some rationality
it's got sensibility it's got the
potency of of being able to commit and
take seriously I think this is all
really really excited domain shift to
I'd like to put two new domains into the
mix get stackoverflow in domains and
slide into the transcendent so so one
domain very concrete actually that I've
lived with a little bit in the past
couple of months is the very specific
whoa
sorry mine Rundle andhe wrote about how
often times that things that are coming
you will first see in the military so
Special Forces is the exploration in the
military domain of the inquiry that you
and I are currently having right right
ordinary forces right if you have
special forces everything that isn't
that is ordinary forces are mostly
around doctrine I probably have a
optimization function around doctrine
eisah you may be multiple different
ordinary forces and you may have the
Marines who have a focus domain that
they're optimizing for and the army that
has several different focused in means
they're optimized before but they have
an established doctrine they execute on
that so this is it has to do with actual
utilization as opposed to potentia an
era and keep efficient in a context
where the domain is relatively well
understood as building realm at all
right so the way that you are successful
between ordinary forces modes is you
have a plan and that plan is a
comprehensive plan that when you've
identified what domain you're in you
pull out the plan and you execute on the
plan
so it's a finite-state machine that has
a series of execution functions a
computational in nature and then he
trained all of the agents to play their
role effectively in the context of this
plant enforced Landers language this
would be an omniscient operator our
computational actual actualization
operator right right Special Forces does
the exact opposite Special Forces you by
definition are planning for any possible
circumstance which means you don't have
a plan you have no notion of what the
domain isn't in fact you may be domain
switching willy-nilly why you may be
diving out of an airplane into the ocean
landing on the beach going into the
jungle heading into a city right and not
even knowing which of those are gonna
happen what's gonna happen which pace
right you're not actually operating in
full uncertainty so Special Forces
adopted the doctrine of flexibility at
the doctrine of relevance the doctrine
of how to be fluid in response to what's
actually happening and embedding
fluidity into the individuals to the
individuals are not now specialized role
players that can be pieces of a machine
that is optimized against a particular
domain but rather are generalists who
live in the space of potentia so instead
of living in the minute actual they live
in the space of pretension and their
expertise is how to move from
pretentious into actuality with the
finite with a very very limited amount
of attention right so you to apply
appropriate or just attention is their
skill set you know I'm in the water what
are the things I need to attend to now
well now I'm on the beach I'm not in the
water anymore what are the things I need
to attend to now where the threats that
are the most meaningful now what are the
opportunities that are most relevant now
like that kind of a capacity as a
special forces capacity okay great slide
next one is um the world is now very
much so paying the price we're having a
hangover from a over-dependence hyper
hyper over dependence on optimization in
actuality efficiency we've become a
hyper efficient therefore hyper fragile
and hyper non-flexible global economy in
ever it means like education families
housing logistics politics it's all like
this super actualized optimize for a
certain subdomain its ordinary forces
and this return this in this room this
forced requirement why we can't we're in
we're in it doubts and we're just gonna
have to learn how to become special
forces and become special forces which I
believe is in is is the new normal
might the new normal is not work
temporarily special fortunes then return
back to actuality but rather the new
normal is we ought to become agents of
that kind we all become sort of Omni
Navy SEALs who can be in any environment
and can adapt fluidly and adaptively to
continuous change because remember not
only have we learned the hard lesson
that an over reliance on optimization is
an unwise choice but also recognize that
we are on a very nonlinear path this
accelerating change the technology that
we've chosen to become dependent on is
every iteration it checked it doesn't
just change the world it changes the
rate of change yeah so the world is
going to continue to be one where to be
Special Forces is the only way to
survive so I'd like to throw those into
the into the I love that I love that I
mean that so that the martial art
metaphors often come to my mind too and
so there's a couple things here one is I
know you're familiar with it and no in
the model that I've worked out with Tim
little Cobb and Blake Richards and Leo
Ferraro relevance realization was
constantly trading between efficiency
and resiliency and and we push as you
say I think we've pushed too far into
efficiency and planning and we've lost
resiliency and coping we so our coping
abilities are very untrained very very
hungry because what we've tried to do is
we've tried to make everything I think
it's both efficiency and also a kind of
security and those are often outlined
together this goes back to the emotional
stability what we're trying to do is you
know can we can we get things as
efficiently non-challenging as possible
if I could put it that way and so coping
so the
the thing about the thing about coping
and the special forces is especially you
you have to get into a state of mind
where you are which doesn't feel very
efficient because what you have to do is
you have to keep various options alive
at the same time you have to have a form
of thinking even when we're talking
notice how we're doing this we like
we're not just getting to the bottom
line what we're doing is we're throwing
out and we're keeping multiple things
alive multiple options multiple ways in
which things can go and where it will
compress towards some convergence but
then we'll open it up again and we'll oh
right and we keep this is the deep
learning cycle which I think is this is
what we're coming out of machine
learning this is how you make a system
really get at coping really good at
making it more adaptive you constantly
cycling we do yes we do gather together
we come to convergence you know because
we have to have points right but at the
same time where we are also committed to
the resilience we're committed to
keeping the options open keeping them
live and what's really interesting if
you take a look and this is another riff
in our culture we have tended to put
aside older people because they don't
have efficient working memory and so we
give them all these tests about how fast
can they come to a conclusion how
quickly can they get the correct answer
and they're say I'll look the decline
but what Lin has showed is yeah but you
know what's wrong with older brains they
keep many more things as potentially
relevant live that's why they seem so
distracted that's why it's harder for
them to come to a conclusion and when
you give them a well-defined problem yes
you out-compete them but if you put you
and them into an ill-defined problem
they out-compete you right and so the
user culture and all of that is also and
you know part of the way in which we've
enacted this you know the way we
marginalize and exclude the elderly and
we there they are just diminished
versions of us and so I think that's
also important that we we start to
remember coping
iliyan see keeping things alive and
taking because role models matter and
what we're talking about paying
attention again to old people as our
model for cognition as opposed to just
the 20-somethings as the model for how
cognition should be operating mmm yeah
there's there's something really how do
I say this yeah I I'm I'm aware of I'm
familiar with I spend I've actually
spent meaningful time with the the
archetype of this other kind which we
could call sport yeah but I used to say
I used to be smart optimizing for clock
speed you're optimizing for quick
quickness and rapid computation now
you're just users taking information and
processing it quickly and it's a very
different thing that happens when you
shift into this other mode yes has a huh
yeah I guess I got wrote about a little
bit med essay thinking you're not
thinking it has a characteristic that it
can seem a bit slow yes
but it's actually not it's it's like
still water runs deep it's deep
more volume of water is moving you just
can't tell yeah exactly
or maybe it's not as obvious you could
tell if you immersed yourself in and
felt the weight of it and I see this
also with a certain set of personality
types it's not necessary strictly age
not create my wife for example it's
great relief and revelation for her to
realize that she was what is known as a
slow processor and I would refer to say
hey take the time you need to take
because my experience is that whatever
comes out of your process will always be
better I rely on that and so if it's if
we're in a situation we have it coming
between an OK solution rapidly is the
thing I'll take that I can get us to 85
percent of the right answer almost
instantaneously but if it's necessary to
actually get a really good answer
then take the time
today and over and over again that has
worked really well it's super
interesting to like just away like her
whole mood now and will clearly be
operating like nine or ten different
modes of knowing and then each one to
kind of do its thing and then kind of
like doing it again in a different way
and she'll well you know work on arch or
she'll go for long walks or she'll be
cooking I should be talking to people
she's just processing it all over the
plates but when something finally
becomes clear it's solid and it's
something can be used to build stuff
with well so there's two things I wanted
to say that because right one is like so
this is educating for virtuous
adaptivity
maybe we can put it together right and
then and add activity shouldn't be
confused or equated to speed of
reactivity this is an again a martial
art thing like the first you know you
got one faster yeah I wanted fast reflex
no you don't you want to have
spontaneous responses spontaneous
responses are ones in which you can
intervene and you can finesse the move
if you just not fast reflexes right you
yeah you can't you can't do it
but if if I if I'm just about to make
the punch right and I decide no I'm
going to flip it like this right um
right go around something that you just
put up at the last second then that's
what we're after we're after so we
shouldn't be confusing I mean we
shouldn't be confusing adaptivity with
speed of reckoning we should be we
should bring bringing out finesse and
then I wanted to bring out what I I
think your you know your wife
exemplifies I think um I hope this is
taken correctly because I I don't like
to use masculine and feminine I try to
use Yang and Yin because masculine
feminine are so politicized but the yin
way of doing things is much more about
that it's much more about deepening
right the resources of resilience before
you respond rather than striking out so
like right and and so you know that I
think we need to
also be bringing in more of the in
aspect into our understanding of this
educational project absolutely and so
yeah so kind of to loop back to an
earlier thread but also to expand it is
is your educational project oriented
towards training managers to run a
culture that somebody else built right
or is it in giving capacity to give
people responsibility for continually
renewing and constructing the culture
that they themselves are living in and
are passing down those are just
different those are completely different
intents and obviously the ladder is how
he builds up to the last and I think
it's really interesting how we seem to
really fallen into a universal pitfall
of becoming the former becoming to which
of the former evaporate managers to
manage a culture that was built by other
people many of whom were in fact no
longer alive so they're even how why or
what it was the basis it's just a weird
place that we find ourselves in but all
of the capacities that you've been
talking about know that we've been we've
been talking about in this dialogue that
show up in this other mode this way they
were talking about it like the special
forces approach fluid response have to
do with responsibility yes yes you are
not you are not merely managing
something you are building it you are
responsible for it how funny one of the
things I've noticed is uh public spaces
in society are usually really sad like
you go to a public park there's usually
trash in the public park right really
really really high functioning
extremists in there it's not the best
whereas often times if you go to a place
that is held by people who have who live
there
the what's the phrase like I remember in
school the teacher would say something
like would you do that in your own house
yeah
the answer of course is no obviously I
wouldn't just throw my trash on the
ground in my own house or if I if I did
I'm not a civic person my mother a
mature person and there's something
about that but there's something about
if I live in a culture that is not my
own culture and I'm merely managing it
and I'm paying other people to take
responsibility for functions and their
each kind of playing a managerial role
it's almost like a feeling of
indifference or a feeling it's the okay
to not take care of it whereas if I
actually am responsible for it one I
feel the burden of that responsibility
but then of course I feel the
responsibility for it if I have agency
to be responsible then you've got a
vital culture that renews it something
keeps itself clean it picks up its own
trash and you know repairs it's broken
and infrastructure and things like that
sorry
that was a good I think that's important
the idea of I mean yeah you're right it
creates a distancing it creates an I hit
relationship with things rather than an
eye though and I like the way you're
picking up on the ability to respond but
also again as you said the ethical
component of responsibility treating
things the way they deserve to be
treated which means firstly and foremost
attending to them in the way they meet
right giving them the time giving them
their the cognitive space yeah right and
so what I'm wondering also if this and
you know more about this than I do but
Zack and I we're talking about this
about trying to move the normativity of
education off beings wholly focused sort
of on the market we're talking a lot
about culture here and one of the death
holding crisis is reminding us is that
you know I think Thomas B Orman is right
we've sort of gotten down to the
de-facto normativity for us is the
market but what we're realizing is no no
that actually sticks within culture and
we've got to remember that and then the
culture ultimately sits within the
environment the ecology and and if we
don't get that back word we're screwed
we're in deep trouble
so what that comes up to my mind given
what I just said and given what you said
is that is you know broadening the
notion of responsibility beyond that
which I own because that's what you're
talking about well as when I've talked
to people about it's a little bit
different here in Canada our parks are
usually trash free but because because
you know we negotiated our independence
we didn't have a revolution right by the
way are the trash free because the parks
are well funded and have lots of paid
people who clean it up or because the
people in the parks clean up the parks
so both so both there is you they're
well funded that people with and there
isn't an objection to that people don't
say no I don't want that I don't own the
park so I don't want to fund it right
there's not that I mean we're talking
about an ideal contrast obviously
there's a continuum here between the two
countries so I hope that's understood
but also if I were to just be in a park
and throw trash on the ground there's a
very good chance somebody would say what
are you doing what are you doing are you
doing my right right and so that's what
I mean about the sense of that we have a
responsibility that's born of
participation you know I'm you know
enculturation which is different than
the responsibility that is born out of
ownership right and the way we're
interacting with market forces I'm not
I'm not saying I'm not a Marxist I'm not
saying oh you're away with the marker
I'm not saying that but I'm trying to
say again we have to situate our
normativity back into what I think
you're putting your finger on that
naughty in fact I want to say it's funny
in the process of enculturation it's the
process of continually evolving
inculturation that right what we're
talking about here that's exactly it
exactly and so so it's this rewind a
little bit and then come back from there
so
what I would say is I would say the
proposition that you previously making
is the exact opposite of Marxist right
okay what Marx Marxism does wrong
I can't think the same as its category
error and it's interesting like it's
exactly the wrong direction is alienates
everyone from responsibility for the
culture I turn to higher culture into
management so I'd like what I'd like to
propose if I can present this notion of
management this notion of managing
something that you do not have
responsibility for then it's not yours
like if I'm managing a company right the
shareholders own it and I manage it like
that relationality that alienation
that's this term right yet Marxism is
does that instead of getting rid of that
it actually makes that ubiquitous I'm
not a lien ated for everything the state
runs everything and nobody our managers
right we're all managers which is
exactly the worst you're actually
pointing in the exact opposite direction
which is just say okay well how come you
can we create a context and by the way
what I want to say here is is obviously
crucial that we not load people with
responsibility but it's not theirs to
carry and I say cannot carry right yeah
yeah I'm not suggesting that what I'm
suggesting is a continuous process of
empowering people to be able to a take
more responsibility and B to discern
what responsibility is theirs and to
take it right so there's a there's a
three distinct things yes yes and this
that that triad those three elements
that empowerment discernment and
responsibility mesh together into a
culture that is a volatile and culture
and this is a culture that is no longer
attached to what it is but rather is
empowered in image what it is becoming
and is always living forward to that
exceeding horizon and this is again so
now we did at the individual level or
the individual level having expertise is
now an extinction event because the
thing you're an expert in is becoming a
commodity and irrelevant having
adaptiveness it
is the new normal but the same thing
just came true for cultures and all
cultures that are biased towards
efficiency bias towards optimization
bias towards stasis bias towards
training managers of what is our an
extinction event it is only those
cultures that are able to enculturate to
develop individuals who are increasing
their capacity to have response to take
appropriate responsibility and then in
there by the way in collaboration with
everyone else they have the capacity at
all as cultures that have this
responsive adaptiveness to what is
becoming right right that's excellent
and I like the way you made the proper
proper reach reformulation of my take on
Marx's and I think you're right about
that that's well said I mean it's been a
long-standing critique of Marxism that
it was just as bad as capitalism at
taking account of culture taking account
of the ecology it didn't know better and
so there's something about shared
presuppositions that we need to be
challenged across the board there yeah
other ways here's a here's a throwaway
but the the critique I had of and by the
way I'm not an expert all on feminism
but the critique I had a feminism is
this there was a point at which feminism
could have chosen to liberate all of us
from shitty jobs but instead we decided
to do is to have all of us men men and
women included both equal in shitty jobs
like boy gosh the road not taken' in
1972 we've been asked if we could have
picked me on the road now we'd all be
sitting with none of us being in shitty
jobs we've been a really better place to
be
well why it became and I get it was a
path dependency on history and
possibility and consciousness but how it
became the thing that the virtue is to
become a director of marketing at a
Madison Avenue advertising firm is an
interesting case study of how bad people
can lead on the wrong path yes
specifically casting aspersions at all
directors of marketing at Madison Avenue
I think that so
so I want to try and get the I guess the
proper these theoretical interface
between we've got these two levels of
scale we're talking about we're talking
about sort of you know how education
being oriented towards evolving and
culturation and odd activity and then we
said that that's going to give giving
people the virtue of you know adaptivity
sensing what's significant being able to
take serious being able to commit
themselves you know a sense of you know
and you know I've talked about this
before a sense of the course of things
we when we have a discussion about faith
right then that virtue of being able to
you know I wear like the way your
faithful to your wife you don't you
don't try and get I'm gonna try to get
my optimal set of beliefs about my life
and I'm gonna try and get that so I can
manage her appropriately because that's
a disaster right now about to happen but
instead what you mean is faithfulness is
I'm going to try and cultivate a potency
a resiliency so that I can adapt and
stay in continuity of contact with her
as she changes I can maintain you know
the continuity of the contact in the
relationship I can constantly evolve as
and afford how she was unfolding so that
notion of faithfulness as opposed to
closure or management and so there's a
bridge from there over and over again
that dichotomy I think just continues to
come up and we can just build a fluidity
of noticing okay to what degree am I on
this path of the closure into whipped
cream on this path of reciprocal opening
yes it's just after every time in every
location yeah exactly there was sort of
the sensitivity towards reciprocal
opening and so again I'm trying to
understand what that means
Enterprise right I don't want to I don't
want to say social engineering because I
think that's the managerial frame of
mind but what would that need for the
disposition of resources and you know
the structuring of institutions that we
used to call education what would it no
pun intended but what would that mean
concretely about that right these are we
D centralizing education
what does it mean you know we try to get
something like okay in the platonic
without me go ahead so should try this
is a really sweet use of a phrase
inverted so you talked about from one
direction this notion of giving the
attention that is just yes yeah okay
flip it around imagine the child is that
object that thing that phenomenon to
which we are endeavoring to give the
attention that is just yeah all right
that's gonna be a core principle of any
future any new education system how do I
truly attend to this being this
unfolding beingness how do I have faith
how do I operate in good faith in
relationship with that with that
developing human any education system
worth its salt must operate in that way
right so I can immediately now show how
our current education system fails it
does not do that it does not give the
child the attention to this is their due
it gives the child the you know whatever
cookie cutter represent repetitive
attention is available in a scalable
hierarchical system where the only way
to give any attention at all is to
repeat and none of it has to do with
what is do so one of course is to work
to invert it is bus boat it is for sure
this book and it's just same we're
describing your relationship with your
wife is bespoke it is it is what of it
so any educational system that is
violent of the future must always take
each individual human as a singular
event and cultivate a context that lifts
them in the in their beingness and
they're becoming this as singular events
all right now this is how you do meta
design by the way I'm going to I'm
describing what is necessary now if it
sounds hard
oh well do bad it's necessary so we have
to work backwards and figure out how we
get that and how we get better at it and
by the way it may be a thousand
generations before we can pull off what
I just described again we're working for
meta design then we'll work on design so
the meta design is we are always going
to be taking every distinct sentient
every distinct human as a singular event
which is on its own evolutionary
developmental trajectory and our job is
to is to create context that allow it to
cultivate it
self in its becoming and it's singular
become which of course means that we
will need to have a network that has
this each node in the network each being
you and I everyone who participates in
this has as first order very high
discernment about what relationships to
create and where to attend to those
relationships what flows across those
relationships so if you imagine a
context imagine a village and that
village every adult and that every child
every person is building an increasing
discernment in exactly this capacity
answer a child that six-year-old is
flowing through the village playing as
is the perfect educational domain our
mode and come across a group of people
who are building a wall and feels
intrigued by that right lesson one and
will question one is this actually the
thing that is your just attention an
inquiry can you can volt abate in that
child and every encounter where their
attention is attending to something an
awareness of a meta awareness is this
the place where my attention is just is
this where I should be attending right
to a relationship is it happens form are
we now have two nodes that are in graph
relationship the group that is working
on the wall in the child let's say for
example and the answer is yes child is
this is this where you should be
attending yes okay great now we have a
bespoke educational opportunity what is
the possibility in this space attention
not actual we're not trying to create a
system that is optimized we're trying to
actually be special forces in the
educational domain an opportunity has
emerged that has an invitation a child's
natural native capacities is oriented
their attention to this space okay great
we now who are working here how do we
sense in ourselves what is the best
possibility that can be made of this
particular moment and there are so many
an infinite number of possibilities in
the moment of building a wall and who
knows what they are only the people on
the ground he didn't have a chance of
knowing what they are so this notion of
do logos this notion of being able to
enter into an opportunity for an
expansion of capacity in our
co-evolutionary journey as the primary
capacity to become an agent of do logos
embedded in every person during the
context of community AHS I think is the
answer right right I think that's right
it's funny yeah you're saying that time
my son
Jason he's living with me right now and
I were watching three through the
pandemic we're watching the old David
Carradine kung-fu series from the 70s
when I watched it as a kid now looking
back and then sharing it with him and
he's really really enjoying it you know
it doesn't have the martial art you know
you know you know of daredevil or
anything like that but what you've gone
I think I mean I mean it's a TV show is
what has implemented cetera but what
he's is resonating with what I'm seeing
in it is exactly what you're talking
about because what what the show is if
you watch it's not primarily a martial
arts share it's an educational show and
the way you're talking about that's why
they do all keep doing the
retrospectives of when he's in the
shaolin temple when he's in the
monastery and right and and the kind of
education he was given and then what he
does when he's interacting with people
is he's doing exactly what you're
talking about
he's naturally enters it and he knows
how you we can convey and communicate
with silence as well as with speech and
he's doing that all the time he's doing
exactly there's that there's that
there's that there's a deep inner
penetration of like spirituality and
this kind of education we're talking
about and it's been really interesting
for me to see millennial my son I mean
obviously there's lunch and - he's my
son he's been influenced by me but
nevertheless seeing how much he like
like yeah there's a ways in which the
show you know like I said the martial
arts are so clunky compared to what you
see you today and you know it's you know
the production values aren't as great
but you know he's he's willing to put
aside all of that because he's getting
like he's getting that sense of you know
I'm learning something here right there
and and and so it would I'm sorry I just
it just just came from my mind though I
was thinking yeah what's happening is
that you know for all the stuff I teach
him sharing this with him and we're
going through it together is exactly the
kind of thing you're talking about it's
kind of this it's kind of this
intersection between you know apprentice
Singh somebody apprentice ting with
somebody and model
with them and also co-creating because
he's also it's not just that I'm
apprentice in him but he's also
affording me seeing something that I
thought I do you know in a renewed way
right away powerful what yeah I think
that that's um you glued together the
term spirituality education I think
that's gonna be a minimum requirement
right right you need to make those terms
become education is spiritual practice
or something along those lines and an
insight I think that comes from that is
to recognize that it is always symmetric
that you know if I'm interacting with a
three-year-old and there is a moment of
educative in that moment it is fully
symmetric right I'm in learning as much
as I'm teaching and how I'm not open to
that if I'm not open to that I'm not
teaching at all I'm teaching is in fact
the lesson that I am NOT a good teacher
yes nor my a good learner right so
that's that's that's one piece the other
I'm mindful now also this character
Foucault and what I'd like what I'd like
to do is I'd like to uh pull out the
virtue I think Luke who had a lot of
really powerful insights and one was he
he he specifically named these eras of
society and maybe I'm actually stealing
a bit from deloitte so if you if you if
you're a delays and you think I'm
standing firm to lawyers then great if
your doors you know that demoys likes
people to steal so I'll do that but he
distinguishes between this notion of the
Society of discipline yeah and when he
talks about in society of discipline as
this initiative vertically integrated
specialization so that one is a teacher
in the context of the school and all
teacher leanness all education is
domain-specific to the institution of
the school right right okay that's gone
I would like to just kill that it's dead
it's no longer and we need to be living
through a little bit longer if it but
not a lot if you gather paying any
attention with schools or trying to do
in the context of the coronavirus of the
pandemic
yeah that's done so what's the thing
that comes after the whole system so
it's a society of discipline meaning
that you are in prison or in the
hospital or at the factory or at the
office right each one of these
and he had his identity structures where
I'm only I'm you know dad at home and
working at work in this new place the
stack goes from being vertically
integrated to being horizontally
integrated so you're now full note right
so I am always in education and my
experience is always open to the
possibility of Education
I'm always parenting matrons has always
opened the possibility of parent I'm
always working when experience olives to
open the possibility of working and I
must maintain in myself each human must
have wholeness of all those
possibilities at least as stem cells and
this is potentials that they can
activate in moments where there's
moments arise so then the question is
this skillful capacity this this I think
you can we keep kind of hitting on the
same things but now the residents just
gets bigger and better of just being
having a discernment and awareness of
what the moment portends right between
you and I there is a moment in that
moment there's a just attention let's
just just say what is the highest
possibility this moment affords and all
of the modalities of human possibility I
can't hug you
so unfortunately hugging is not one of
them although it would be good if we
could can I break bread with you I can
talk with you and that's neat because
you actually a very far away it's a
really interesting possibility
so that's threat to what degree can we
constantly kind of dancing through the
encounters that are possible and then in
the moments that emerge out of that
possibility
how do them play into the emerging them
it's a possibility to create the highest
possibility that is available to to in
good faith right in relationship that is
towards the unfolding of the highest in
each of us so that as we shift from
those encounters and move each of these
ripples each of these activist moments
just putting increasing possibility an
increasing discernment and just get and
you think about the potential that
builds and something that has that
orientation instead of sucking the
potential out of the universe and moving
into actual to try to get this material
that makes us feel safe we're actually
building a recombining
potential that is blowing up in
potential because every encounter
expands the potential more so even than
the actual
that's fantastic I love that imagery
that's really cool I like that idea
about instead of trying to collapse to
safety we keep I mean you're talking
a kind of metaphysical empowerment where
power look I'm going back to the
original meaning of power which is a you
know a potential that you can actualize
as needed right and die Nana
Dynamis right that kind of notion of it
so I'm also trying to think about what I
like that idea I mean one of my
pedagogical principles as a teacher is
that I'm doing my best teaching when I'm
sharing learning with you rather than
disseminating information to you so if I
get to my place if I can get to a place
where I'm experiencing insight or flow
in teaching then I'm actually doing
right if I can get on the edge of the
induction right to draw forth educe
right if I can get into a place where
things are being drawn from me that I
didn't see before as I'm teaching so
right so the distinction between me
teaching you and me learning within the
teaching you it's completely blurred
back for me is is good good teaching but
what that calls to mind then the way you
talked about that I mean cuz I think I'm
increasingly sort of zeroing in on the
critique the way our culture has
collapsed my deepest goes with the
managerial imperative you've been
talking about how we've collapsed into a
monologic understanding of the mind the
mind works mana logically rather than
dialogical II although there's now just
increasingly good evidence that we work
much better dialogic Lee than we do mana
logically right that the monophasic that
there's sort of one state of
consciousness we should always be in and
that's sort of the ultimate I'm thinking
about sort of the Enlightenment heritage
it gave us you know clip this sort of
you know your mock you you know there's
this one state of consciousness and then
think about how much this is like a
managerial state right and and then
there's there's a monologue right
because I'm managing right and then and
then they're you know and I said there's
monophasic and there's monological and
then monolithic it's only oriented
propositional right but there's there's
a fourth one I want to try and get here
that you're putting your finger on there
resonates with those three the degree to
which people write the degree to which
people see themselves what do I want to
say the almost like an ecology they see
themselves like the thing you did right
you know what Arendt said about Eichmann
and the Nazis they took that vertical
integration into compartmentalization
that allowed them to do great evil you
know he's a great father at home and
then he's the manager of the numbers oh
right right yeah right right that
there's that point there's there's a
that verticality there Zaman ISM of the
verticality with it I'm you're trying to
break you see what I'm trying to get it
that people don't have a Monell identity
right right that they're always there
they're always there to do multirole
it's right you don't you know more sort
when you take the stairs I don't
actually fight with this stance this
stance is multi out it's a it's a it's a
nexus that allows me access it activates
in particular many possible states that
I can get to and I'm not I'm not trying
to hold this what I'm trying to do is
get to that because it activates them
and accesses them so what I need to do
this I can do that you see what I'm
trying to get out I'm trying to get at
that that there's absolutely you try to
break up with you know the monophasic
monolithic monological mind and also
this this this completely
compartmentalize you know mono identity
that people I'm right now under dad
right now in the future but what you
said was no no I'm multi act I've got
this stance where I'm concerned about a
nexus place in which all of my potential
roles and potentially new roles are
accessible and equitable for me in this
fluid and adoptive manner how does that
sit with you yeah absolutely the martial
arts been unfortunately nice because
obviously if I truly want to be
effective at martial arts but I want to
make is that every move increases the
potential for the next move right yes
yeah so its energy is increasing I'm not
actually deploying energy I like
exercise it's actually every move
creates a potential for more possibility
yes that's like that's it that's that's
a very nice concrete version of the same
story and and yes yes yes yes
so I'm trying to get out of sort of a
multi aptness of identity that's what
I'm trying okay cool check this out all
right so I tried it all right so this is
really cool stuff you guys have been
talking about what do I do
okay an example learn some new yeah
you'd fit at home right now you probably
if you're not then you probably should
be or maybe you do sounds very important
if you are then ignore what I just said
but one of the games I'd like to get out
there is the game of what did I learn
during quarantine what ten new skills
that I not have that I learned because
right now you can learn all kinds of
stuff it can be simple like you learn
how to cut somebody's hair you can learn
how to make sourdough bread you can
learn all kinds of new skills well one
of the very first things is to enter
into the consciousness that your
possibility for self learning a new
skill is largely unfettered yeah each
entrance be tensions like these pools
where it's instead of steps it's like
smooth speech and you have to dive into
learning how to fly rocket ships first
order learn how to do something simple
first you can teach yourself you can
teach yourself and bite off more than
you can chew right next step get
yourself little bit more but everybody
right now I should be taking it as a
primary ethical obligation that instead
of watching Netflix by the way kung fu
is fine and I'm gonna recommend that to
my kids it's a great idea it's not about
Brad about that but instead of instead
of real sort of binge watching with
friends I'll use that as an example of
what not to do watch it teach yourself
new skills educate all kinds of skills
make cheese make yogurt repair stuff
like but the point is not the skills
you're learning the point is the skill
to learn skills and not go behind is the
consciousness of the capacity to become
a stem cell and by the way meta skills
like okay watch some YouTube videos on
how to have really rich dialogue with
your parent with your partner become a
better partner how to become a better
parent
those are meta skills that are our
skills that you should definitely
learning now so like the the capacity of
just to take opportunity and saying geez
everybody's kind of stuck in this weird
limbo space what should I do
well the first thing you should do is
that like learn how to learn like that's
the thing I can do you now you've
actually had this weird opportunity to
be going back to college as it were um
take advantage of it sorry so that's
look a little words from our sponsor if
you if you're looking for a thing to
actualize what John and I are talking
about that right there is a very
straightforward at for sure
off
the kimmy14 by most people right now
that's excellent and I also like that
I mean that advice is great I also like
the the meta advice you gave in it you
you you you you told people to like you
advised people who should say to move
between learning and meta learning
learning about learning right and and
this is that compression variation thing
right again what do all the learnings
have in common right and yeah and then
and then what and then look at the
variations and then okay use the way
they have in common to acquire a new
skill a new variation and then read oh
now I know new things that they all have
in common and that affords me of
learning a new skill and you know do
that cycle where yeah what's invariant
so you could learn something you can
transfer and learn a new thing you can
introduce more you're basically enacting
evolution right you know vary your
processing then call from it and then
from that vary it again and and so forth
and like involve you like literally
evolve your learning don't just learn I
think that's also what you were saying
it was so cool exactly the ball learning
and then and then the very top of that
stack we have Socrates which is a noble
health in this process of learning of
evolving your learning and coming into
this relationship of development it's of
evolutionary relationship with life one
of the things is the only invariant the
thing that will always be there is
yourself and so you will be able to
notice what is it what am I in this
context what is my trajectory I learned
so far in quarantine is how to grill as
it turns out it was a needed thing
really so I start grilling and I was I
went from kind of like okay pretty darn
good not great but pretty damn good and
I noticed that I liked it it was a skill
that I enjoyed having a having added to
to Who I am so they told me a little bit
about myself and I learned some
interesting things about how I learned
but when you learn about how you learn
that tells you a lot about who you are
oh I think thanks I think that's a great
suit rotting inside I mean and
Christopher Moore a nice book on product
self-knowledge and Gonzalez and others
as I'm doing research for after Socrates
that's the thing you know
we've got to give up the romantic not
idea that we know ourselves by
introspecting or reflecting on our
autobiography what you how to best know
yourself right is biologically when when
when you're learning and being
challenged and you know what do you care
about what can you come to care about
what do you commit to what can you come
to commit to this is how you actually
deep you you most learn about yourself
the way you're talking about you'd look
you learn about yourself while you're
learning about other things especially
when you're learning about other people
that is how yeah yes that's how you best
get to self-knowledge yeah and then then
you can play the role of being a steward
of emergent culture and not a cog
aspiring to be a manager in a static
extinction area culture I think that's
well what I think that's a good place to
maybe draw to a close I think that's
really I think this was really really
excellent yeah I'd like at some point
I'd like to have a follow-up
conversation sort of because we've I
think this was nice the way this round
it out but we round it back on Socrates
and then I maybe next time come into you
okay what does this mean for a dialectic
and dear lotus-eyed like because I think
you're right I think it is I mean I got
the idea from you that dialectic and via
logos are the meta psychic technology
they're at the top of the stack as you
put it I'd like to know as you know I'm
just I'm and I'm trying to enact
Socrates I'm talking about not in the
sense of you know trying to refute
everybody but I'm trying to talk to
everybody who I think is in good faith
about trying to wrestle with this trying
and trying to practice it and commit to
it they want to understand what I want
to understand as deeply as possible what
this is because I think you're right I
think it is at the top of the stack in
some very very important sounds good I
you know I'm journeying right now right
now I'm in a temporary stopping point
where I have a I year that had some
connectivity I hope it was okay I don't
know if this
actually recorded at any with the felt
like we were able to know you were
periodically the video you were
periodically Lurie the audio was mostly
constant it was one or two very brief
gaps yeah but I think actually by our by
next week certainly in two weeks I'll be
again to a to an oasis that has good
connectivity so hopefully we can
continue to just to roll our canoe
together yeah I'd like that
well you let me know you let me know
because you know you're in transit I
mean in transition so let me know the
two roads are related of course that
you'd let me know you know if next week
or two weeks from now is better for you
just let me know well dude okay they
talking about thank you so much my
friend I'm going to stop the recording
now